I used to have this recurring dream
أعتدت على هذا الحلم المتكرر
where I'd walk into a roomful of people,
أينما أمضي الى غرفة مليئة بالناس،
and I'd try not to make eye contact with anyone.
وأحاول أن لا أنظر في أعين أحدهم،
Until someone notices me,
إلا أن يلاحظني أحدهم.
and I just panic.
أصاب حينها باالرعب.
And the person walks up to me,
ثم يتوجه هذا الشخص إلي،
and says, "Hi, my name is So-and-so.
ثم يقول: "مرحبا اسمي كذا وكذا.
And what is your name?"
ما هو اسمك؟"
And I'm just quiet, unable to respond.
وأتسمر حينها غير قادرٍ على الكلام.
After some awkward silence, he goes,
ثم بعد مضي وقت على هذا الصمت الغريب يسأل،
"Have you forgotten your name?"
"هل نسيت اسمك؟"
And I'm still quiet.
ولا أزال صامتاً.
And then, slowly, all the other people in the room begin to turn toward me
ثم بعد ذلك يلتفت إلي كل من بالغرفة ببطئ
and ask, almost in unison,
ويسأل جميعهم في الوقت ذاته،
(Voice-over, several voices) "Have you forgotten your name?"
(صوت خارجي، عدة أصوات) "هل نسيت اسمك؟"
As the chant gets louder, I want to respond, but I don't.
وكلما علت أصواتهم أريد أن أجيب لكن لا أستطيع،
I'm a visual artist.
أنا فنان تشكيلي.
Some of my work is humorous,
بعض من أعمالي هزلية،
and some is a bit funny but in a sad way.
والبعض الآخر منها مضحك على نحو محزن،
And one thing that I really enjoy doing
وأحد تلك الاشياء التي أستمتع بفعلها
is making these little animations
هو عمل الرسوم المتحركة
where I get to do the voice-over for all kinds of characters.
حيث أؤدي بنفسي أصوات جميع الشخصيات.
I've been a bear.
كنت مرة دُباً.
(Video) Bear (Safwat Saleem's voice): Hi.
(فيديو) دب (صوت صفوت سليم) : مرحباً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Safwat Saleem: I've been a whale.
(صفوت سليم): وقد كنت حوتاً.
(Video) Whale (SS's voice): Hi.
(فيديو) حوت (صوت صفوت): مرحباً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
SS: I've been a greeting card.
(صفوت سليم): وكنت بطاقة تحية.
(Video) Greeting card (SS's voice): Hi.
(فيديو) بطاقة تحية (صوت صفوة): مرحبا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
SS: And my personal favorite is Frankenstein's monster.
(صفوت): والشخصية المفضلة لدي هي الوحش (فرانكشتاين).
(Video) Frankenstein's monster (SS's voice): (Grunts)
(فيديو) الوحش (فرانكشتاين) (صوت صفوت): (زمجرة)
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
SS: I just had to grunt a lot for that one.
صفوت: كان علي أن أزمجر كثيراً لهذه.
A few years ago, I made this educational video
قبل عدة سنين أعددت هذه الفيديو التعليمي
about the history of video games.
عن تاريخ ألعاب الفيديو.
And for that one, I got to do the voice of Space Invader.
ومن أجل ذلك كان علي أن أؤدي أصوات غزاة الفضاء.
(Video) Space Invader (SS's voice): Hi.
(فيديو) غزاة الفضاء (صوت صفوت): مرحباً.
SS: A dream come true, really,
(صفوت): حلم وتحقق، فعلاًَ.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And when that video was posted online,
وعندما نُشر الفيديو على الإنترنت،
I just sat there on the computer, hitting "refresh,"
كنت متسمراً أمام الحاسب أضغط على "تحديث"،
excited to see the response.
متحمساً لرؤية التعليقات،
The first comment comes in.
وقد كان أول تعليق،
(Video) Comment: Great job.
(فيديو) تعليق: عمل رائع.
SS: Yes!
صفوة: نعم!
I hit "refresh."
ثم أضغط على "تحديث"
(Video) Comment: Excellent video. I look forward to the next one.
(فيديو) تعليق: فيديو ممتاز، أتطلع لرؤية المزيد.
SS: This was just the first of a two-part video.
(صفوت): لقد كان هذا الجزء الأول من فيديو على جزئين،
I was going to work on the second one next.
كنت بصدد بدء العمل على الجزء الثاني،
I hit "refresh."
ضغطت على "تحديث"
(Video) Comment: Where is part TWO? WHEREEEEE? I need it NOWWWWW!: P
(فيديو) تعليق: أين الجزء الثاني؟ أييييين أنا أحتاجه الآآآآآآن،
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
SS: People other than my mom were saying nice things about me,
(صفوت): تخيل أن هنالك أشخاصاً آخرين غير أمي يتحدثون بأشياء جيدة عني،
on the Internet!
على الإنترنت!
It felt like I had finally arrived.
لقد شعرت وكأنني أخيراً وصلت.
I hit "refresh."
ثم ضغطت على "تحديث"
(Video) Comment: His voice is annoying. No offense.
(فيديو) تعليق: صوته مزعج، مع احترامي.
SS: OK, no offense taken. Refresh.
صفوت: مع احترامك حسناً، تحديث.
(Video) Comment: Could you remake this without peanut butter in your mouth?
(فيديو): تعليق: هل يمكنك أن تعيد عمل هذا بدون زبدة فول سوداني في فمك؟
SS: OK, at least the feedback is somewhat constructive. Hit "refresh."
صفوة: حسناً، لابأس على الأقل نقد بناء، وضغطت "تحديث"
(Video) Comment: Please don't use this narrator again
(فيديو) تعليق: أرجوكم لا تستعملوا صوت هذا المعلق مجدداً
u can barely understand him.
بالكاد تستطيع فهمه.
SS: Refresh.
(صفوت): تحديث.
(Video) Comment: Couldn't follow because of the Indian accent.
(فيديو) تعليق: لم أستطع المتابعة بسبب هذه اللهجة الهندية.
SS: OK, OK, OK, two things.
(صفوت): حسناً، حسناً، شيئان،
Number one, I don't have an Indian accent,
الأولى، لكنتي ليست هندية،
I have a Pakistani accent, OK?
لكنتي باكستانية، مفهوم؟
And number two, I clearly have a Pakistani accent.
والثانية، لكنتي باكستانية بوضوح.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But comments like that kept coming in,
لكن استمرت مثل هذه التعليقات في الورود،
so I figured I should just ignore them
لذلك فكرت ربما علي تجاهلها
and start working on the second part of the video.
والبدء بالعمل على الجزء الثاني من الفيديو.
I recorded my audio,
سجّلت صوتي،
but every time I sat down to edit,
ولكن في كل مرة أجلس وأبدأ بالتعديل،
I just could not do it.
أجد أنني لا أستطيع ذلك.
Every single time, it would take me back to my childhood,
في كل مرة، أعود بذاكرتي إلى طفولتي،
when I had a much harder time speaking.
عندما كنت أعاني بشكل كبير حينما أتحدث،
I've stuttered for as long as I can remember.
كنت أتمتم كثيراً على ما أذكر.
I was the kid in class
كنت ذلك الطالب في الصف
who would never raise his hand when he had a question --
الذي يستحيل أن يرفع يده إذا ما كان لديه سؤال --
or knew the answer.
أو لو كان يعرف الإجابة.
Every time the phone rang,
في كل مرة يرن فيها الهاتف
I would run to the bathroom so I would not have to answer it.
أركض هارباً للحمام حتى أتحاشى رفعه،
If it was for me, my parents would say I'm not around.
واذا كانت المكالمة لي يرد والداي بأنني غير موجود.
I spent a lot of time in the bathroom.
قضيت وقتاً طويلاً في الحمام.
And I hated introducing myself,
وكرهت تقديم نفسي،
especially in groups.
خاصةً في المجموعات.
I'd always stutter on my name, and there was usually someone who'd go,
دائماً ما كنت أتلعثم عند قول اسمي ليقول شخص ما،
"Have you forgotten your name?"
" هل نسيت اسمك؟"
And then everybody would laugh.
ثم يبدأ الكل بالضحك.
That joke never got old.
تلك النكتة لاتهرم أبداً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I spent my childhood feeling that if I spoke,
أمضيت طفولتي معتقداً أنني إذا ما تحدثت،
it would become obvious that there was something wrong with me,
سيكون من الواضح أن هنالك خطب ما فيّ،
that I was not normal.
أنني غير طبيعي.
So I mostly stayed quiet.
ولذلك في الأغلب بقيت صامتاً.
And so you see, eventually for me to even be able to use my voice in my work
وكما ترون إلى أن أصبحت اُعد أعمالي بصوتي
was a huge step for me.
وكانت تلك خطوةً كبيرةً بالنسبة لي.
Every time I record audio,
في كل مرة أسجل فيها صوتاً،
I fumble my way through saying each sentence many, many times,
أتحسس طريقي عن طريق تكرار الجملة مرات ومرات،
and then I go back in
ثم أعود
and pick the ones where I think I suck the least.
وأختار الصوت الذي باعتقادي هو الأقل سوءاً.
(Voice-over) SS: Audio editing is like Photoshop for your voice.
(صوت خارجي) (صفوت): تحرير الصوت يعادل عمل فوتوشوب للصوت.
I can slow it down, speed it up, make it deeper, add an echo.
أستطيع أن أبطئه أو أُسرّعه أو جعله أعمق أو إضافة صدى.
And if I stutter along the way, and if I stutter along the way,
وإذا ما تلعثمت في جزئية،
I just go back in and fix it.
أعود واُصلحها.
It's magic.
إنّه سحر.
SS: Using my highly edited voice in my work
(صفوت): استخدام صوتي المعدل جداً في عملي
was a way for me to finally sound normal to myself.
كان بالنسبة لي أخيراً الطريق لأبدو طبيعياً لنفسي.
But after the comments on the video,
ولكن بعد التعليقات على الفيديو،
it no longer made me feel normal.
لم أعد أشعر وكأنني طبيعي.
And so I stopped using my voice in my work.
ولذلك توقفت عن إستعمال صوتي في عملي.
Since then, I've thought a lot about what it means to be normal.
ومنذ ذلك الحين وأنا افكر كثيراً في ماذا يعني ان أكون طبيعياً.
And I've come to understand
وقد فهمت
that "normal" has a lot to do with expectations.
أن "طبيعي" ينطوي عليها الكثير من التوقعات.
Let me give you an example.
دعوني أعطيكم مثالاً.
I came across this story
مررت بهذه القصة
about the Ancient Greek writer, Homer.
عن الكاتب الإغريقي القديم (هومر).
Now, Homer mentions very few colors in his writing.
و(هومر) هذا ذكر القليل جداً من الألوان في نصوصه.
And even when he does,
وحتى عندما يذكرها،
he seems to get them quite a bit wrong.
يبدو وكأنه رآها بطريقة خاطئة،
For example, the sea is described as wine red,
على سبيل المثال، البحر يصفه بالخمر الأحمر،
people's faces are sometimes green and sheep are purple.
وجوه الناس أحياناً يصفها بالخضراء، والخرفان بالبنفسجية،
But it's not just Homer.
لكن ليس وحده (هومر).
If you look at all of the ancient literature --
لو نظرت إلى جميع الأدب القديم --
Ancient Chinese, Icelandic, Greek, Indian
الصينية القديمة أو الآيسلندية أو اليونانية أو الهندية
and even the original Hebrew Bible --
وحتى التوراة اليهودية الأصلية --
they all mention very few colors.
جميعهم ذكروا القليل من الألوان.
And the most popular theory for why that might be the case
والتفسير الشهير لهذه المسألة قد يكون
is that cultures begin to recognize a color
أن الحضارات بدأت تتعرف على اللون
only once they have the ability to make that color.
فقط عندما أصبحت قادرة على إنتاج هذا اللون.
So basically, if you can make a color,
إذاً بالأساس إذا ما استطعت صنع لون،
only then can you see it.
حينها فقط تستطيع رؤيته.
A color like red, which was fairly easy for many cultures to make --
لون مثل الأحمر والذي كان من السهل صنعه لحضارات كثيرة --
they began to see that color fairly early on.
تمكنوا من رؤية ذلك اللون مبكراً.
But a color like blue, which was much harder to make --
ولكن لوناً مثل الأزرق والذي كان من الصعب صناعته --
many cultures didn't begin to learn how to make that color
العديد من الحضارات لم تكن قادرة على إنتاج هذا اللون
until much later.
إلّا قبل فترة قريبة.
They didn't begin to see it until much later as well.
وكذلك قدرتهم على رؤيته ابتدأت قبل فترة قريبة.
So until then, even though a color might be all around them,
حتى ذلك الحين، رغم أن اللون قد يكون حولهم في كل مكان،
they simply did not have the ability to see it.
هم ببساطة لم يمتلكوا القدرة على رؤيته.
It was invisIble.
كان لا يُرى.
It was not a part of their normal.
لم يكن جزءاً من حياتهم الطبيعية.
And that story has helped put my own experience into context.
وقد ساعدتني تلك القصة على فهم تجربتي أكثر.
So when I first read the comments on the video,
ولذلك عندما قرأت تعليقات الفيديو للمرة الأولى،
my initial reaction was to take it all very personally.
كانت ردة فعلي الأولى بأن أخذتها على نحو شخصي.
But the people commenting did not know
ولكن هؤلاء الناس الذين علقوا لم يعرفوا
how self-conscious I am about my voice.
كم أنا واعٍ بحال صوتي.
They were mostly reacting to my accent,
هم على الأغلب يقصدون لهجتي،
that it is not normal for a narrator to have an accent.
أنه من غير الطبيعي لمعلِق أن تكون له لهجة.
But what is normal, anyway?
لكن ماهو الطبيعي على كل حال؟
We know that reviewers will find more spelling errors in your writing
نعلم أن المراجعين سيجدون أخطاءً إملائية أكثر في نصوصك
if they think you're black.
إذا ما ظنوا أنك أسود.
We know that professors are less likely to help female or minority students.
ونعلم أن الأساتذة غالباً ما لا يساعدون الطالبات أو طلاب الأقليات
And we know that resumes with white-sounding names
ونعلم أن السيّر الذاتية التي تحمل أسماء البيض
get more callbacks than resumes with black-sounding names.
يتم الإتصال بهم أكثر مقارنة بالسود
Why is that?
ولكن لماذا؟
Because of our expectations of what is normal.
هذا بسبب توقعاتنا لما هو طبيعي.
We think it is normal
نعتقد أنه شيء طبيعي
when a black student has spelling errors.
عندما يخطئ طالب أسود بالكتابة.
when a female or minority student does not succeed.
عندما تفشل طالبة أو طالب ينتمي لأقلية.
And we think it is normal
نعتقد أنه طبيعي
that a white employee is a better hire than a black employee.
أن موظفاً أبيض هو أفضل للوظيفة من موظف أسود.
But studies also show that discrimination of this kind,
وأظهرت الدراسات أيضا أن التمييز من هذا النوع،
in most cases, is simply favoritism,
في معظم الحالات، بكل بساطة ليس إلا تفضيل،
and it results more from wanting to help people that you can relate to
وينتج عن رغبة لمساعدة أناس أنت تنتمي إليهم أكثر
than the desire to harm people that you can't relate to.
أكثر من كونه رغبة لإلحاق الضرر بأناس أنت لا تنتمي إليهم.
And not relating to people starts at a very early age.
وعدم الإنتماء لجماعة يبدأ من سن صغيرة جداً.
Let me give you an example.
دعوني أًعطيكم مثالاً.
One library that keeps track of characters
إحدى المكتبات التي تتابع نمط الشخصيات
in the children's book collection every year,
في مجموعة كتب الأطفال كل سنة،
found that in 2014, only about 11 percent of the books
وجدت في عام 2014 أن ما نسبته11% فقط من هذه الكتب
had a character of color.
تحتوي على شخصية سوداء.
And just the year before, that number was about eight percent,
وفقط في السنة التي سبقتها كان ذلك الرقم تقريباً 8%،
even though half of American children today come from a minority background.
على الرغم من أن نصف أطفال أمريكا اليوم يأتون من خلفيات أقلية.
Half.
النصف.
So there are two big issues here.
إذاً لدينا هنا مشكلتان شائكتان،
Number one, children are told that they can be anything,
المشكلة الأولى، يقال للأطفال أن بإمكانهم أن يصبحوا أي شيء،
they can do anything,
بإمكانهم فعل أي شي،
and yet, most stories that children of color consume
ومع ذلك، معظم القصص التي يشتريها الأطفال السود
are about people who are not like them.
هي عن أناس لايشبهونهم.
Number two is that majority groups don't get to realize
المشكلة الثانية، المجموعة الأكبر لم يتسنى لها أن تفهم
the great extent to which they are similar to minorities --
أنها وبدرجة كبيرة تتشابه مع الأقليات الصغيرة --
our everyday experiences, our hopes,
تجاربنا اليومية، وآمالنا،
our dreams, our fears
وأحلامنا، ومخاوفنا
and our mutual love for hummus.
وحبنا المشترك للحمص.
It's delicious!
إنه لذيذ!
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Just like the color blue for Ancient Greeks,
بالضبط مثل اللون الأزرق بالنسبة لليونانين القدماء،
minorities are not a part of what we consider normal,
الأقليات ليست جزءاً مما نعتبره طبيعياً،
because normal is simply a construction of what we've been exposed to,
لأن الطبيعي ببساطة هو نموذجنا الذي بنيناه لما أعتدنا النظر إليه،
and how visible it is around us.
أو بقدر ماهو مرئي من حولنا .
And this is where things get a bit difficult.
وهنا تشتبك الأمور قليلاً.
I can accept the preexisting notion of normal -- that normal is good,
إما أن أتقبل الفكرة القائمة على أن الطبيعي هو الجيّد،
and anything outside of that very narrow definition of normal is bad.
وأن أي شيء عدا ذلك النطاق الضيق لتعريف الجيد يعتبر سيئاً.
Or I can challenge that preexisting notion of normal
أو أستطيع تحدي الفكرة القائمة للجيد
with my work
بعملي
and with my voice
وبصوتي
and with my accent
وبلهجتي
and by standing here onstage,
وبوقوفي هنا على هذا المسرح
even though I'm scared shitless and would rather be in the bathroom.
حتى وإن كنت مرتعباً جداً وأفضل لو كنت في الحمام،
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
(Video) Sheep (SS's voice): I'm now slowly starting to use my voice
(فيديو) خروف (صوت صفوت): والآن بدأت تدريجياً في استخدام صوتي
in my work again.
في أعمالي مجدداً.
And it feels good.
وذلك يعطيني شعوراً طيباً.
It does not mean I won't have a breakdown
هذا لايعني أنني لن أنهار مجدداً
the next time a couple dozen people say that I talk
في المرة القادمة عندما يقول مجموعة أنني أتكلم
(Mumbling) like I have peanut butter in my mouth.
(يغمغم) وكأن هناك زبدة فول سوداني في فمي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
SS: It just means I now have a much better understanding
(صفوت سليم): يعني ذلك أن لدي الآن فهم أكبر
of what's at stake,
لما تتطلبه المخاطرة،
and how giving up is not an option.
وكيف أن الإستسلام ليس خياراً.
The Ancient Greeks didn't just wake up one day and realize
لم يستيقظ اليونانيون القدماء يوماً ما ليكتشفوا
that the sky was blue.
أن لون السماء أزرق.
It took centuries, even, for humans to realize what we had been ignoring
لقد تطلب الأمر قروناً، حتى تسنى للبشر ملاحظة ما كانوا يتجاهلوه
for so long.
لمدة طويلة.
And so we must continuously challenge our notion of normal,
ولذلك يجب علينا تحدي مفهومنا لما هو طبيعي باستمرار،
because doing so is going to allow us as a society
لأنه بفعلنا هذا سنسمح لأنفسنا كمجتمع
to finally see the sky for what it is.
برؤية حقيقة السماء أخيراً.
(Video) Characters: Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you.
(فيديو) شخصيات: شكراً شكراً، شكراً شكراً شكراً.
Frankenstein's monster: (Grunts)
الوحش فرانكشتاين: (يزمجر)
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
SS: Thank you.
(صفوت سليم): شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)